Francis LeJau Parker Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Francis LeJau Parker Papers 1905-1935
MSS50856
Parker, Francis LeJau, 1873-1966
5,500 items
16 containers
6.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
U.S. army officer and government official. Copies of letters, telegrams, dispatches, and reports, records of Parker's military service, pamphlets, documents, and other papers relating to his service as an army officer and attaché during World War I and later as a member of special missions in Latin America.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Parker, Francis LeJau, 1873-1966.
Organizations
Romania. Armata.; Russia. Armii︠a︡.; United States. Bureau of Insular Affairs.
Subjects
Elections--Nicaragua.; Hurricanes--Puerto Rico.; Tacna-Arica question.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
Chile--Boundaries--Peru.; Latin America--Foreign relations--United States.; Nicaragua--Politics and government--1909-1937.; Peru--Boundaries--Chile.; Philippines--Foreign relations--United States.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Russia--Politics and government--20th century.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Latin America.; United States--Foreign relations--Philippines.
Occupations
Army officers.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of Francis LeJau Parker, U.S. army officer and government official, were given to the Library of Congress by his nephew, Louis T. Parker, in 1966.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Francis LeJau Parker Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Francis LeJau Parker are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1873, June 24 Born, Abbeville, S.C.
1894 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1915 General Staff corps
1916 Attaché and observer with Russian army
1918 Commanding officer, 119th Infantry, 171st Infantry Brigade
1919 Head, Visitors’ Bureau, American Expeditionary Forces
1921 1923 Military attaché to Mexico
1924 Member, United States-Mexico Claims Commission
1925 1926 Member, Tacna-Arica Arbitration Commission
1928 Vice chairman, National Board of Elections, Nicaragua
1929 1933 Chief, Bureau of Insular Affairs
1936 Retired from active service
1966, May 16 Died, Charleston, S.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Francis LeJau Parker (1873-1966) span the years 1905-1935 and consist mainly of official material gathered in connection with his duties during World War I and as a member of special missions to Latin America, especially in the Tacna-Arica dispute in 1926 between Chile and Peru and in the Nicaraguan elections of 1928. Much of the material is printed or mimeographed and often includes maps and handwritten notes. The collection is organized by subject and therein by topic or type of material. An addition is focused largely on files relating to Mexico and the Philippines and some general correspondence and miscellaneous reports and memoranda.
The collection contains reports by Parker made while on duty with the Romanian and Russian armies in 1916 and 1917 and estimates by him of Russia’s political future. The collection also contains staff lectures on battles and campaigns of the war. Other material includes accounts of a disputed plebiscite in the Tacna-Arica area in 1926, and voluminous notes, drafts, and reports of American supervision of the presidential elections in Nicaragua in 1928. Parker was vice chairman of the election board. Still other material pertains to American assistance to Puerto Rico during a hurricane of 1929. Parker’s tour as chief of the United States Bureau of Insular Affairs from 1929-1933 is reflected on files relating to the Philippines. An addition contains more material on the Philippines and also a monograph and others items pertaining to Mexico.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by subject and therein by topic or type of material.
Container List
- World War I (Box 1)
  - Romanian army (Box 1)
    - Observer, 1916 (Box 1)
    - Maps of front, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Russia (Box 1)
    - Articles, 1917 (Box 1)
    - Military attaché, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Russian front; maps, 1917 (Box 1)
  - American Expeditionary Forces; general orders, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Battle history (Box 1)
    - Argonne, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Chateau-Thierry, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Marne, 1918 (Box 1)
    - St. Mihiel, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Soissons, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Verdun, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Maps, 1918 (Box 1)
    - General résumé, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Army General Staff College (Box 2)
    - Second course (Box 2)
      - Parts 1-3 (Box 2)
      - Parts 4-6 (Box 3)
    - Fourth course, parts 2-5 (Box 3)
    - Argonne battle (Box 3)
- Post-World War I (Box 4)
  - Pershing, John J., report with maps, 1918 (Box 4)
  - United States (Box 4)
    - Occupation of Luxembourg, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Casualty lists by division, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Visitor’s Bureau, 1919 (Box 4)
    - Administrative (Box 4)
    - Battlefield guides (Box 4)
    - Congressional tour (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
  - Army Center of Artillery Studies, 1919 (Box 4)
  - General situation maps, 1919 (Box 4)
- Tacna-Arica dispute (Box 5)
  - Background material, 1921 (Box 5)
  - Background messages, 1925 (Box 5)
  - Review of dispute, 1922-1926 (Box 5)
  - Memoranda and notes, Oct. 1925-June 1926 (Box 5)
  - Plebiscitary Commission (Box 5)
    - Addresses by members (Box 5)
    - Executive session notes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous resolutions (Box 5)
  - Duties of registration and election boards (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, Peruvian view (Box 6)
  - Personnel affairs (Box 6)
  - List of Peruvians in disputed area (Box 6)
  - Talks by Parker (Box 6)
  - Terrorism (Box 6)
  - Press news (Box 6)
  - Maps of disputed area (Box 6)
  - Printed matter (Box 6)
    - Election regulations (Box 6)
    - Dictionary of plebiscite (Box 6)
- Nicaragua (1928) (Box 7)
  - Historical background printed (Box 7)
  - National Board of Elections (Box 7)
    - Initial activities (Box 7)
    - Appeals (Box 7)
    - Ballots (Box 7)
  - Electoral forms (Box 7)
    - Regulations, printed (Box 8)
    - Regulations, drafts (Box 8)
    - Memoranda of the board (Box 8)
    - Minutes of the board (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes of the board (Box 8)
  - United States Mission (Box 9)
    - Drafts of messages to secretary of state (Box 9)
    - Memoranda by Parker (Box 9)
    - Memoranda, miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Personal affairs (Box 9)
    - Projects (Box 9)
    - Report of the chairman (Box 9)
      - Sections 1 and 2 (Box 9)
      - Section 3 (Box 10)
      - Photo section (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Maps of area (Box 10)
    - Letter of Moncade to the secretary of state, copy (Box 10)
  - Puerto Rican Hurricane Relief Commission, 1929 (Box 11)
- Bureau of Insular Affairs, relating to the Philippines, 1929-1933 (Box 11)
  - Commercial affairs (Box 11)
  - History of United States occupation (Box 11)
  - Independence movement (Box 11)
  - Information, printed (Box 11)
  - Miscellany (Box 11)
  - United States expenditures, 1931 (Box 11)
- Addition (Box 12)
  - General correspondence, 1928-1934, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Memoranda, reports, and statements, 1928-1933, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Mexico (Box 13)
    - General, 1905, 1925, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Monograph, circa 1930, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 13, Box 14)
  - Philippines (Box 14)
    - General, 1928-1935, (3 folders) (Box 14, Box 15)
    - H.R. 7233 “Philippine Independence Bill,” 1932 (Box 15)
    - S. 3080 “Vandenberg Bill,” 1932, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 15, Box 16)
    - S. 3377 “Hawes-Cutting Bill,” 1932, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Puerto Rico, 1928-1933 (Box 16)